[SPEAKER_00]: It's the most fundamental context of the holy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said himself, like the sea has only one taste of salt, so the dhamma has only one taste of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, you can take that in a sort of general descriptive manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can also take that in a manner of quite a
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite an acute form of correct contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, develop the theme of being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maintain it, sort of, maintain it in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have it endure in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't lose perspective on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you had faith to begin with,
[SPEAKER_00]: In the Buddhist teaching, they offer you possible way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means you will also, if you don't lose perspective, have faith in all the other instructions He gave.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reasons for celibacy, the reasons for virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be as hard, because you have faith, and you will see it pertaining to the goal, because you have that perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why faith is also... could also be enough for somebody to make effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't necessarily need to have it all figured out, but if you have faith in the right instruction, and you do it rightly, but that doesn't mean you can sacrifice your perspective on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the faith can help you if the perspective hasn't been compromised, if the purpose hasn't been obscured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you a monk?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or why are you practicing dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: To be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you always keep that at the back of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you can get to differentiate more and more things that are then compatible with it and things that are not incompatible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And above all, that's how you can also become aware of your own responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like your own habits of craving that revolve around random things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll say, wait a minute, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now you have perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what's important to me, to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here I am,
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the purpose of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And I can't seem to be able to stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you lost perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: You regain perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stopping, restraining becomes effortless or certainly requires less effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, gaining perspective makes things a lot easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gaining perspective and maintaining perspective makes things more easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the purpose is not obscured or it's regenerated.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like even, as we mentioned that the other day, like even in the lay world of people who are not necessarily interested in practicing Buddhism, like the motivational speakers and so on, talk about finding the purpose for your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because without it, you're going to be depressed, or you'll be just wandering aimlessly, or just scratching your central itch, day in, day out, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But finding a purpose gives you that meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then makes actions much more easier to do, duty easier to do, restraint, enduring things much easier to do, because you have a greater purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can make a practice out of maintaining, through contemplation, maintaining in the back of your mind, not actively, I want to be free from suffering, I want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just remind yourself and then let it endure without forgetting about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not actively thinking about it, but not forgetting about it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the practice of mindfulness in a nutshell.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could ask yourself, from time to time, maybe, what is the point?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the point of practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can, like, re-evaluate, not in a sense of re-evaluate, oh, what am I, what am I doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that, if necessary, sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you want to be really just maintaining
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the direction of your practice, that you already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... that's... that practice of questioning we discussed before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You question yourself as a form of contemplation, not to necessarily find the right answer, but more like to induce the right attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will then bring that perspective back, or clarify it, or introduce new perspectives.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be given the right answer, because it's not like a quiz question.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like discerning the things that are already there, but you need to see them with the right type of eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to recognize them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to recognize the nature of impermanence, the nature of non-ownership and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all there already.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not recognizing it means it's not there for you, because it's not being seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have a question like
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't even need to be anything specific or technical.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as we said, you remind yourself or you ask yourself, why am I practicing?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the purpose?
[SPEAKER_00]: I've been doing this Buddhist practice for a number of years.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the purpose of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how far you got into that practice, how much you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can always re-ask yourself that question.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you do it rightly, you will just re-establish the perspective or just remind yourself that that perspective is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, it's going to result in mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your question is, why am I practicing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you're a beginner or not a beginner, you ask yourself that, and don't jump at the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't rush.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, because of this... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, what's the point of this?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you'll see that the answer is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you wouldn't have been doing it for all these years.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, as the point always was, freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't feel, perhaps, that you're free from suffering enough,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can press the questions further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, not just so that you can find the right answer that will please you, but more like that, through that attitude of questioning, you will start to look in the direction, eh... different from the ready-made answer that would come your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: The question that will inevitably then have to result in in greater perspective, eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might be more ambiguous perspective, and that's what people fear, to question their own beliefs, their own efforts, because
[SPEAKER_00]: By putting it in question, means you're already questioning... well, you're already implying that it could have also been invalid.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I must not question it then.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how I will not think about a possibility of me being wrong, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you always question yourself, that becomes your perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how actually you cannot be affected, if a thing does change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you haven't been emotionally invested in it and certainly you haven't invested like a form of... well, invested by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, I ignore this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not going to question this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because simply putting it in question, that ambiguity causes me anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I will not question it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's completely the opposite attitude of the attitude you should have if you want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you give me an example?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the example would be, why am I practicing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the answer to that is no, you know the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I fundamentally, ultimately beyond suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the answer is yes, great.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the answer is no, or I'm not sure, means, okay, so all these efforts I've been making, yet I'm still not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perhaps I was wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like that the Buddha's teaching was wrong, but perhaps I haven't been doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, you might now, because, you know, all the investment of your effort and emotionally charged practice that you've been doing for a number of years, it will make that person uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you start questioning it like that, it's going to make you uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if these 20 years of my meditation methods and techniques, and I'm not free from suffering,
[SPEAKER_00]: What if... what if I've been doing it wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: Could I start again?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sooner you start that questioning, the less... less of an emotional investment it will become, if you've been doing it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, if you question it from the start, or if you start questioning it as soon as you become aware of that you should question it, it's... it's still a good thing, because it will prevent you from proliferating further, if it were the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, if it were not the wrong way, you would have been free from suffering by now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you re-evaluate, but not like, oh, but what if... yeah, I might have been wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, what is my purpose?
[SPEAKER_00]: To never be wrong or to be free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: To be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter even if for a hundred years I've been wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I can be right again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I know that everything I've done is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, it's less likely that I'll repeat the same mistakes, because I admitted it to myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you never question it, never admit it, you will then blindly just go and keep repeating the same thing, that you deep down inside know it doesn't work, because it hasn't free you from suffering after all this time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even Ajahn Chah said himself, if you don't become a Sotāpanna in the first five years of practice, you're not doing it right.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't get the right view within the first five years of becoming a monk, committed, you're not doing it right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's quite accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not doing it right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you should really, like, re-evaluate quickly,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the more you invest in the wrong effort, the harder it will be to undo it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because more conceit gets involved, more sense of self, and also, like, more of that, like, oh, I'm not gonna look at this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's becoming... the more you ignore it, the more unpleasant it will be to face it later on.